<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tractatus de jure regnandi, &amp; regni: or, The sphere of government, according to the law of God, nature, and nations. / By VVilliam Ball, Gent.</title>
            <author>Ball, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E309_36</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112149</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 51:E309[36])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tractatus de jure regnandi, &amp; regni: or, The sphere of government, according to the law of God, nature, and nations. / By VVilliam Ball, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Ball, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Natural law --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112149:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112149:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Honourable, Major Generall SKIPPON,</hi> William Ball <hi>of</hi> Barkham, <hi>wiſheth all good ſucceſſe and happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T Your being in <hi>Redding,</hi> about what time the Kings forces relinquiſhed that place in <hi>May</hi> 1644. I preſented unto You a paper, <hi>De jure Regnandi, et Regni,</hi> wherein was contained the heads and chiefe points of that Subject, and therein I promiſed to give farther ſatisfaction, which I hope I have now effected to the ſatisfaction of all indifferent men; and I have thought fit to dedicate it to Your Honour, to whom <hi>I</hi> firſt of all tendered the <hi>Epitome:</hi> remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <date>October 27. 1645.</date>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours ſervant</hi> William Ball.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112149:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112149:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Tractatus De jure Regnandi, &amp; Regni:</hi> OR, The Sphere of Government, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any there are (too many at this day) who <hi>velis remiſque,</hi> or rather <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> do contend that the Kings Prerogative power (as it is denominated) is like to <hi>Terra Auſtralis Incognita,</hi> which is vaſt and unknowne, and in a manner unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, extending from the <hi>Equator</hi> (as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Cogmoſgraphers deſcribe) to the Pole <hi>Antartick</hi> in latitude, and of an huge, yet uncertaine longitude, ſome ſuppoſe it anſwers to all the degrees; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo they would have the Kings Prerogative power vaſt, and unknowne, and in a manner unlimited, <hi>extending from the Equator of Law</hi> 90 <hi>degrees to the Pole or Period of ſole Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government in latitude; and in longitude ſo huge and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, as that it anſwers to all the degrees of ſelfe end, to doe every thing that Power would admit.</hi> Others there are, who ſuppoſe that the power of Parliament is like the <hi>Great Sea,</hi> which not only environs the Land, and enters into all the creeks and harbors, whereſoever its flux or currents can make
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112149:3"/> way; but is thought alſo to extend from <hi>Pole to Pole,</hi> and to anſwer to all degrees of longitude by one denomination, or another, as it were boundleſſe; for even ſo they would have the Parliaments power, <hi>not only to environ by limitation the King, and by their flux and currants of conſultation to enter into all creeks and harbours of private policie, to make them benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for King and People; but it muſt be thought alſo to extend from Pole to Pole of Arbitrary juriſdiction,</hi> quaſi ad placitum de omnibus, <hi>and (as theſe men would have it) to all degrees of abſolute Authority, and as it were boundleſſe.</hi> But theſe men muſt give mee leave to tell them, that I cannot thinke the Kings <hi>Terra Auſtralis Incognita</hi> of Prerogative power, or the Parliaments <hi>Great Sea</hi> of <hi>Iuridicall power</hi> to be ſo unlimited or boundleſſe; or if they were, yet as the Aire environs both the Land and the Great Sea, and gives life to all the creatures in them, and without which Aire both Land and Sea would be deſolate, and of no uſe; even ſo the Peoples good in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, environs both King and Parliament, and gives life to all their actions, and without which Peoples good, both King and Parliament would be <hi>null,</hi> and of no uſe; and to make good this my opinion, or Aſſertion, I have inſerted (as compendiouſly as I could) what of right generally belongs to King, Parliament, and People; ſubmitting my ſelfe to more ſolid reaſons or Arguments if given or produced.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is certaine, that <hi>all power is of God,</hi> Rom. 13. and that it is derived from him either by <hi>extraordinary</hi> calling, or appointment, as was that of <hi>Moſes, Aaron, &amp;c.</hi> or by <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> which is either <hi>naturall,</hi> as that power which a Parent hath naturally (grounded upon humane reaſon, as well as the Word of God) over his childe; or Nationall, as that power which Potentates, or States have over their Subjects or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And of power Nationall or Politicall, there are ſeverall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112149:3"/> 
               <hi>ſpecies</hi> or forms, <hi>viz.</hi> Monarchy, Oligarchy, Ariſtocracy, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy, or mixt, or compounded of theſe forms: Monarchy is either unlimited, or limited; <hi>unlimited,</hi> is where <hi>tam jus Regni abſolutê quâm Regnandi,</hi> as well the Law of the Realm abſolutely, as the Law of Reigning, or ruling over, reſides in one alone, as it did in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and is ſaid to bee in ſome of the Kings of the Eaſt, and of Affrica at this day; <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited</hi> is where <hi>Ius Regnandi, et Regni conditionatê,</hi> the Law of Reigning, or ruling over, and of the Realme conditionally reſides in one alone, as it ſeemeth to have been in <hi>Darius,</hi> Dan. 6. who made not the Decree concerning ſole petitioning himſelfe, by himſelfe alone (as did <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Image, Dan. 3) but by advice of his Princes, and Councellours; nor could he alter his Statutes at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as appeares, Dan. 6. v. 15. and ſuch like limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs are the Great Turke, the King of Perſia, and it may be the Emperours of Ruſſia and Aethiopia; for theſe Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, albeit they can <hi>ad arbitrium,</hi> command to ſtrangle, or deprive one man of his life, and he is deprived, and diſpoſſes another of his goods, and he is diſpoſſeſſed; yet can they not at their pleaſure <hi>diſanull,</hi> or alter their Religion, or funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Laws of their Nation: and this power of Monarchy unlimited, or limited, hath been impoſed upon enſlaved Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, either by violent and unnaturall conqueſts, as it was by the Aſſyrian, Caldean and Perſian Monarchs, &amp;c. or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and conſent (or agreement as it were) to undergoe, and be governed by ſuch power, as in Turky, Muſcovy; and in a manner in theſe dayes, in France, Caſtile, and Florence.</p>
            <p>Oligarchy, is where <hi>Ius Regni, ſive Imperii, vel Reipublicae,</hi> the Law of the Realme or Empire, or Commonwealth, is intruſted to, and reſident in a few, as it was in the Roman <hi>Triumviri,</hi> who were not abſolute, for they could not alter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112149:4"/> at their pleaſure the Roman Lawes, but were rather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alterable.</p>
            <p>Ariſtocracy, is where <hi>Ius Regni, ſive Imperii vel Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae,</hi> the Law of the Realme, or Empire, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, is reſident in the Princes or chiefeſt of the people, and this power may be either inherent, and as it were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, as it is in Venice; or intruſted, or limited, or qualified, as in Holland and Geneva; for the Ariſtocraticall Power, or <hi>States</hi> in thoſe parts, give ſome account of their actions to ſatisfie the people.</p>
            <p>Democracy (to ſpeake properly) is where <hi>Ius Reipublicae,</hi> the Law of the Commonwealth reſides in the people, who have not only a perpetuall power of nominating what Rulers and Governours they pleaſe, but alſo of dictating, or preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing by what <hi>rules</hi> they will be governed by; and of this Democracy, if there be not an Exact, yet there is a near form in the <hi>Cantons</hi> of Switzerland.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mixt, or compound formes of Government conſiſt ſometimes, and in ſome places, of Monarchy and Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as in Poland; or of Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy, as in England: in Poland the Ariſtocracy hath been moſt prevalent: in England for the moſt part the Democracy hath prevailed: but I intend not to inſiſt or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance what hath been <hi>defacto,</hi> or what ought to be <hi>de jure;—</hi>in England <hi>jus Regnandi</hi> is the Kings, he hath it introduced by conqueſt, which albeit that barely of it ſelfe it created not a juſt Title, yet joyned with the conſent of the Nation it <note place="margin">Conqueſt without ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all warrant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God (as had the Iſraelites againſt the people of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan) or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a juſt N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tionall Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is unjuſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> compained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with two gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſi is, pride a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> covetouſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and is direc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oppoſite to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Law of natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in that it de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priveth othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liberty and propriety.</note> did; and to ſignifie the Kings introduction by conqueſt, the words <hi>â conqueſtu,</hi> are to this day inſerted in all <hi>Fines:</hi> The King hath his <hi>jus Regnandi Dei, non populi gratiâ;</hi> and ſo hath the King of Poland (although he be elective) his <hi>jus Regnam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Dei gratiâ,</hi> but not without, but by conſent of his Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112149:4"/> in England it is our Kings by birthright: neither Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or people can, or ought to deprive him of it, as long as he protecteth them according to the Lawes, and conſerveth them (to the utmoſt of his power) from forraigne ſlavery or ſubjection.—And as <hi>Ius Regnandi</hi> is the Kings in England, ſo <hi>Ius Regni Actuals, &amp; Potentiale,</hi> is the peoples in generall (that is to ſay, the people in their ſeverall Degrees have right to their Lawes in <hi>Beeing,</hi> and by their Feoffees, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, whom they intruſt to give their conſents, they have alſo right to the Lawes in <hi>Poſſe,</hi> or to be) the King cannot, nor ought to <hi>nullifie</hi> the Law or Lawes at his pleaſure: for as in a Lordſhip or Mannor, the Law of Right of inheriting belongeth to the Lord, his heires and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; of which Right of inheriting, the Tenants of a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor cannot, nor ought not to deprive the Lord, his lawfull heires and ſucceſſors; and alſo in the ſame Lordſhip or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, the Law, or right of cuſtomes belongeth to the Tenants, their heires or ſucceſſors, of which right of cuſtomes the Lord cannot, nor ought to deprive the Tenants, their heires or ſucceſſors; even ſo is it, or ought to be in this Kingdome of England between the King and the people in generall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And having ſaid that <hi>Ius Regnandi</hi> is the Kings, I will firſt briefly inſert what <hi>Ius Regnandi</hi> comprehends; it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends a power ordinary, and extraordinary; both limited, and qualified, neither abſolute; and this laſt, ſome call <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative:</hi> The ordinary power of a King of England is to <hi>convene</hi> or aſſemble Parliaments, and to ratifie or diſanull what they ſhall generally approve, or diſaprove of for the <hi>good</hi> of the Kingdome, or any eſſentiall part or member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for as a <hi>Body politick</hi> the King is obliged <hi>in foro conſcientia,</hi> to doe any thing for the good of the Kingdome, provided that it deſtroy not his owne right: The <hi>ordinary</hi> power alſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112149:5"/> of a King of England is to nominate, and conſtitute Judges, and Civill Magiſtrates, Commanders and Officers Military; provided that ſuch as concerne the <hi>Publicke,</hi> be not generally diſliked by the <hi>Publicke;</hi> becauſe although it belongs to the King to appoint who ſhall ſuſtaine his <hi>perſon,</hi> or <hi>vices ſuas ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere,</hi> yet for as much as thoſe perſons doe meddle with, and are converſant about the affaires of the Kingdome more then of the King, if Kingdome or Publick therefore diſlike them, the King ought <hi>in fore conſcientiae,</hi> to diſplace them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſuch as they may like of. It is in the Kings ordinary power alſo, to confer dignities, and to diſpoſe of thoſe things that meerly concerne his owne <hi>Intereſt;</hi> I ſay <hi>meerly,</hi> becauſe the Crowne is the Kings <hi>Intereſt,</hi> but not meerly his <hi>intereſt,</hi> he is owner of it but for his naturall life, neither can he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of it. The King hath relation to the Crowne but for his naturall life, and then <hi>cedit alii.—</hi>The <hi>extraordinary</hi> (or Prerogative) power of a King of England, I define thus, <hi>Eſt virtus ſive potentia in perſonâ Regiá benefaciendi ſibi, &amp; populo in quibus leges non ſufficienter ſe extenſas habent;</hi> a power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xi extenſas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>â leges ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>per inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad ſummu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctum, cui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dinantur ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt etſi n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>per dicunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dum illius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſionis.</note> or beeing in a King, whereby he may doe good to himſelfe, and people, in things wherein the Lawes doe not ſufficiently extend; and this power may be ſaid to be <hi>intra legem, ſed non delege,</hi> this power is environed by the Law, and hath the ſame end that the Law hath, <hi>viz.</hi> the good of King and people; from this power extraordinary it follows, that if a ſudden invaſion ſhould be before a Parliament could be conveened, or aſſembled, (a thing not very likely) the King for the raiſing of forces for defence, might impoſe taxes upon his Subjects, ſuch as were uſually impoſed upon them by conſent of former Parliaments in ſuch like caſes; and for the doing or accompliſhing thereof hee may iſſue forth his Proclamations ſufficiently ſtrengthned with penall injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112149:5"/> But he ought forthwith to call, or aſſemble a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe the Publicke is involved as much, or more then himſelfe, and that being aſſembled, not to do any thing without their conſent: for to ſpeake truly, <hi>a King of England is but in nature of an high Steward of the Kingdome by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,—</hi>By this extraordinary power alſo a King may in ſome caſes pardon (as they call it) or rather ſuſpend or exempt the penalties due to convicted or condemned felons or tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, for the Law only provides puniſhment due to ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders; but the King may exempt the puniſhment, where the parties vertues, or deſerts have formerly countervailed his miſdeeds; or otherwiſe where there is hope and poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he may by his good endeavours benefit the King, and Country as much as he hath dampnified them; for theſe cauſes ought to be the end of exempting from puniſhment delinquents for matters or crimes of an high nature; and in ſuch things as theſe conſiſts the Kings extraordinary power or Prerogative.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yet there is one thing greatly inſiſted upon, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by ſome to be a moſt eſſentiall part of the Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, and that is the Kings <hi>negative voice</hi> in Parliament; for my part I muſt confeſſe that I could never be otherwiſe ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but that all Statutes, or Acts of Parliament here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, were made by conſent of our Kings or Queens; and that the ſaid Statutes, or Acts doe themſelves either <hi>explicitly,</hi> or <hi>implicitly</hi> demonſtrate as much; for if it be not inſerted in any Act or Statute, <hi>Be it therefore enacted by the Kings</hi> (or Queens) <hi>moſt excellent Majeſty, with aſſent of the Lords and Commons, &amp;c. then is it dictated, be it therefore enacted by Authority of this preſent Parliament, &amp;c.</hi> wherein the King is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended as the head or chiefe of his Parliament, without whoſe conſent (it ſeems) ſuch Acts had not beene in their full
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112149:6"/> force and vertue,—not withſtanding I do not ſee that becauſe the Kings conſent doth give force or vertue to an Act or Statute, that therefore his non-conſent, or <hi>negative voice</hi> is a moſt eſſentiall part of his Prerogative or power extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but rather of his ordinary power: and I conceive moreover power extraordinary or ordinary to conſiſt rather in reaſon <hi>poſitive</hi> then <hi>negative, in beeing</hi> rather then in <hi>non beeing,</hi> and conſequently in the Kings power <hi>to conſent, and Act,</hi> rather then in his power to <hi>non conſent and non-act,</hi> which upon the matter, is but <hi>ens negativum,</hi> a deniall of acting, enacting, or coenacting with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hath free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er to doe at be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; yet the tribute of Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ominated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lingneſſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but from power of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, if willing; though the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g have free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or diſſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, even as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tick, yet the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thority can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bee deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ated from non-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gneſſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſent, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>facting, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illing.</note> wherefore concerning the Kings negative voice in Parliament, I ſtate the caſe thus; <hi>viz.</hi> that his conſent is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary, or unneceſſary to the conſummating of an act in Parliament; if unneceſſary, to what end ſhould it be inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted upon? if neceſſary, then is his conſent either voluntary, &amp; free (as in reaſon it may ſeem to bee, as well as the conſent of either Houſe of Parliament) or elſe the King is tyed and obliged, not only <hi>in foro conſcientiae,</hi> but <hi>jure determinato</hi> to give his conſent; this laſt cannot be made appeare; for a King of England hath power to write, if willing to give his conſent <hi>Le Roy It veult,</hi> or if unwilling, <hi>Le Royle aviſera</hi> (as for that alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation which ſome bring, <hi>viz.</hi> that the King never writes, <hi>Le Roy le neult,</hi> or the King will not, it ſeemeth to me of no great conſequence <hi>for if the King may as a Politick body adviſe as he pleaſeth, he may conſequently not will, till he pleaſe;</hi> wherfore his conſent-muſt be voluntary, that is to ſay the King hath free power to <hi>conſent or diſſent,</hi> even as he is a Body Politick, not withſtanding that the vertue of his <hi>Authority</hi> conſiſts in his <hi>poſsitive power of conſent,</hi> or being able <hi>to Act, &amp;c.</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Furthermore for my part I conceive, that although the King have free power to conſent or diſſent (even as he is a Politick body) and that his conſent give force and vertue to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112149:6"/> an Act and Statute (as aforeſaid) yet his diſſent doth not or cannot fruſtrate, or make void an <hi>Ordinance</hi> concluded of and avouched by both Houſes of Parliament, and generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of by the whole, or major part of the Kingdome; and the reaſon is, becauſe the Parliament is the repreſentative Body of the Kingdom, intruſted by the Kingdome, and may therefore conclude of, and conſtitute what ſhall ſeem expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for the good of the Kingdome; and ſuch conſtitution, or Ordinance (generally admitted as aforeſaid) hath, or ought to have the nature and vigor of Law, for <hi>Ius Regni tâm Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale, quâm Potentiale,</hi> is the peoples in generall, they are inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted in that, the Kings intereſt conſiſts <hi>in jure Regnandi:</hi> but to this ſome it may be will object, that almoſt all immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and priviledges to Cities, and eſpecially to Townes corporate, have been conferred by our Kings; yea ſome will not ſticke to affirme that all the liberties of the Kingdome have been granted by our Kings, and that therefore it may ſeem unjuſt that any conſtitution or ordinance ſhould have the nature or vigor of Law, <hi>nolente Rege,</hi> to this I anſwer, that almoſt all ſuch immunities or priviledges are included <hi>Radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> in the generall liberties of the <hi>ſhares</hi> or <hi>ſhires</hi> of the Kingdome, ſo that they are not meer <hi>Grants</hi> of our Kings, but <hi>Treaſures</hi> of the Kingdome in more ſpeciall manner <hi>applied</hi> by our Kings to ſome places, and perſons; and as touching all liberties of the Kingdome to have been granted by Kings, I confeſſe I was once inclined to that opinion in reſpect of the conqueſt; but having conſidered that conqueſt barely of it ſelfe createth no juſt Title (as formerly inſtanced) and that the Laws and liberties which this Kingdome now enjoyeth were upon the matter <hi>exiſtent</hi> before the conqueſt; &amp; that the Conqueror, his heires and ſucceſſors were obliged, <hi>ſtricte in foro conſcientia,</hi> to conſerve and maintaine them (albeit they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112149:7"/> violated too many of them) I ſay theſe things conſidered, I cannot finde how the <hi>liberties</hi> of the Kingdome ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from our Kings, but that they are the peoples in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall by right, even as the Crowne, or <hi>Ius Regnandi</hi> is the Kings by birthright; yet admitting that ſome immunities or priviledges were granted by our Kings to ſome places and perſons, or to the Kingdome in generall; may not the people, or (their feoffees in truſt) the Parliament make the beſt uſe of ſuch Grants, as well as Kings have made uſe of Grants from their Subjects? And why ſhould then the Kings Grants of priviledges or liberties (if any ſuch have been) impeach the Subjects in generall, or Parliament from doing what they may doe <hi>jure Regni</hi> for their generall good; any more then the Subjects Grants to Kings ſhould impeach them from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they may doe <hi>jure Regnandi</hi> for their owne good? ſurely there can no reaſon be ſhewne; ſo that for my part I conceive that <hi>Ordinances</hi> in nature as aforeſaid have, and ought to have <hi>the force and vigor of Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. And I intend now by way of reaſon, to inſtance the generall benefit and liberty, which the Subjects of England have by the Law, or rather <hi>their</hi> Law (I exclude not the King from any benefit thereof, but only from power of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation) The Law here in England (to comprehend all ſpeciall Lawes in one generall terme) is (as I conceive) <hi>A rule ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by common conſent, by which all men from the higheſt to the loweſt (according to their ſeverall degrees) are to regulate their actions:</hi> to this, both King and people have conſented; by this, both King and people are preſerved; with this, both King and people are united, and as it were linked together: This Law is the true <hi>Robur Britanicum,</hi> whereof the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law is the root and ſtock; and the Statutes, Acts and Ordinances of Parliament are the branches, which at ſeverall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112149:7"/> times upon ſeverall occaſions, have ſpred themſelves to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace the Subjects of this Kingdome, under which they might in peace repoſe: Now the Subjects of this Kingdom, which live under this Law of common conſent, may be conſidered either as the Body <hi>eſſentiall,</hi> and ſo all naturall or native per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what degree ſoever in all Counties, Cities and Towns corporate, and whereſoever within the limits of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are comprehended; or elſe the Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may be conſidered as the Body repreſentative, and ſo the Parliament is only intended conſiſting of Lords or Peers <hi>(quaſipares inter ſe)</hi> and of Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, for the Counties, Cities and Townes corporate: Theſe Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, are elected by the <hi>Democraticall</hi> body of Freeholders, and ſuch like of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and doe <hi>repreſent,</hi> or <hi>vices ſuas gerere</hi> (if the people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confuſion or diſorder could aſſemble together, there were no need of ſuch election) ſo that theſe are the true <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative</hi> Body <hi>Democraticall</hi> of this Kingdome: the Lords are in nature of a Body <hi>Ariſtocraticall,</hi> and the King in form of a Monarch: and theſe three <hi>(viz.</hi> King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons) are in themſelves ſo indifferently, and exactly compoſed without exceſſe or defect <hi>ab origine,</hi> that as ſoule and body make but one entire man, ſo theſe three make but one entire <hi>power</hi> of government, the which (if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects or exorbitances ſhould not, or doe not diſtemper, as diſeaſes doe ſometimes the ſoundeſt bodies, is without any flattery or vain-glorious praiſe, the moſt excellent known form of government in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This power aforeſaid may enact any thing <hi>in beneficium Regni,</hi> for the benefit of the Kingdome, be it generall or ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, &amp;c. but this power <hi>in detrimentum libertatis, aut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietatis generalis ſubditerum Angliae,</hi> cannot doe any thing;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112149:8"/> not any thing I ſay to damnifie the generall liberty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the Subjects of England, and the reaſon is, becauſ the Engliſh are <hi>ſubditi potius, quam ſubjecti,</hi> ſuch as have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put themſelves under a law by common conſent, then enforced to undergoe a Law.—Wherefore I conceive the L. <hi>Digby</hi> to be greatly miſtaken, who affirmed that <hi>a King of England enſphered in his Parliament was as abſolute as any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the Eaſt;</hi> ſome Monarchs of the Eaſt can command to ſtrangle one, and he is ſtrangled; and to deprive another of his goods, or eſtate, and he is deprived; and this they can doe <hi>ad placitum,</hi> without ſhewing any cauſe; but the King and Parliament in England cannot doe ſo; thoſe Monarchs can, and ſome of them have, and doe make Lawes that all their ſubjects eſtates ſhall be at their owne diſpoſalls; <hi>viz.</hi> that <note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Subſidies and the like, do not diſpoſe of the Subjects eſtates in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>ad placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> but only apply equally ſo much of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as ſeems convenient <hi>(in neceſſitatem Regni, &amp;c.)</hi> the neceſſity of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſuch like.</note> they may take from whom they pleaſe, what they pleaſe, all if they pleaſe, <hi>ad placitum;</hi> but in England the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament cannot doe ſo; for the King (as aforeſaid) is but in nature of high Steward of the Kingdome by inheritance, and the Parliament ſeoffees in Truſt; and both tyed by the great Indenture of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to conſerve the generall liberty and propriety of the people: And it is to be noted, that (ſince <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was confirmed, which upon the matter, is but an Abridgement or <hi>Epitome</hi> of the liberties and rights of the Subjects of England before the conqueſt, which liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and rights are grounded upon the Law of God and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon) when any King of England would have extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſupplies from the people, that (the Parliament being conveened) the King hath given or ſhewne ſome probable or ſeeming reaſons why he deſired, or had need of ſuch ſupplies, and the Members of Parliament (I meane thoſe of the Houſe of Commons) at their returne to the places which intruſted them, have likewiſe ſhewne or manifeſted ſome generall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112149:8"/> or cauſes to the people, why ſuch extraordinary ſupplies were by them granted. (And ſurely were there now an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count taken, and given of the extraordinary and vaſt ſupplies levied on the eſtates of the people, it would give a great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction) ſo that neither King or Parliament did at any time take <hi>ad placitum,</hi> but <hi>ad neceſsitatem,</hi> nor did the people other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe grant any extraordinary ſupplies of mony.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But ſome it may be will object, and ſay, ſuppoſe the King and Parliament ſhould make an act that they would &amp; might diſpoſe of all the Subjects eſtates in England (themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, or not excepted) and conſequently that they might take from whom they pleaſe, what they pleaſe, all if they pleaſe, <hi>ad placitum;</hi> what remedy might the Subjects have? I anſwer that for my part, I ſuppoſe it almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the King and Parliament ſhould doe ſuch a thing; but admitting of a kinde of <hi>impoſsible poſsibility,</hi> I anſwer fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in ſuch caſe, the Counties, Cities, and Townes corporate might and ought firſt to petition againſt ſo great an injury, and if not remedied then they might <hi>declare and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> againſt ſuch an act; if violated then they might defend themſelves by Armes; for if the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> Body of the Kingdome, may in the behalfe of the Kingdome, raiſe Arms for the defence of themſelves and the Kingdome, may not the <hi>eſſentiall?</hi> is not the cauſe more noble then the effect, in that it gives being to the effect? doe not the Counties, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Townes corporate give <hi>being,</hi> or a <hi>well-being</hi> to the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes by intruſting their <hi>power Iudiciall</hi> to them? And yet by repoſing or granting ſuch Truſt, they doe not diſinveſt themſelves of their <hi>right natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> (no more then one that paſſeth an eſtate to feoffees in Truſt for ſome cauſes and conſiderations, diſinveſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the uſe intended or reſerved) ſo that they may defend
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112149:9"/> their liberties and proprieties even by law of <hi>Nature,</hi> which no ſpeciall or Nationall Lawes can <hi>nullifie,</hi> unleſſe men will become, or be made ſlaves, and loſe the <hi>right of Nature.</hi> And beſides it is an Axiom Politicall, <hi>ubi nulla protectio, ibi nulla ſubjectio;</hi> if therefore the King or Parliament, or King and Parliament ſhould make an Act, that they might diſpoſe of all Subjects eſtates <hi>ad placitum,</hi> as aforeſaid, <hi>deficiunt â prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione;</hi> they faile or fall from the protection of the people; and then the people may <hi>deficere â ſubjectione,</hi> and protect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their liberties and proprieties even by Law Politicall.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But ſome will farther object that it may be, that the Counties, Cities and Townes corporate, doe intruſt all their power both <hi>Iudiciall</hi> and <hi>Naturall,</hi> fully and wholly as it were, to the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, at their electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, promiſing and covenanting to ſtand to all that they ſhall doe in Parliament, &amp;c. And they will it may be object, and ſay moreover that the King and Parliament are the <hi>Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> power in England, and that they may as well make a Law <hi>to diſpoſe of all Subjects eſtates in</hi> England, <hi>ad placitum, &amp;c.</hi> as they have made, and can make Lawes concerning Religion, and the like.—I anſwer, that albeit the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Cities, and Townes corporate, doe intruſt their power <hi>Iudiciall</hi> (not naturall) to the Knights, Citizens, and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, and promiſe to ſtand to what they ſhall doe, yet they intruſt it <hi>in beneficium Regni, nonperniciem</hi> (that is the proper and adequate object and end of their truſt) and they promiſe to ſtand to what they ſhall doe in <hi>matters diſputable,</hi> whether <note place="margin">Religion is a matter diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> they be Actuall, or <hi>de facto,</hi> or <hi>Potentiall,</hi> wherein the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may be either <hi>benefited</hi> or <hi>damnified,</hi> and of ſuch things the people make them their Judges, but not in <hi>matters indiſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,</hi> wherein without any diſpute the Kingdome would be wholly damnified, and enſlaved, and deprived of its <hi>naturall</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112149:9"/> 
               <hi>right</hi> (as in the King and Parliament having a power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of all mens eſtates <hi>ad placitum,</hi> as aforeſaid, of ſuch things they make them no Judges: and the word <hi>Repreſent</hi> inferres as much, for to repreſent, or <hi>alterius vices gerere</hi> doth not import (as ſome would have it) to be an abſolute <hi>Iudge</hi> or <hi>Vmpire</hi> in all things, (for then he doth not repreſent, or <hi>vices gerere,</hi> but is abſolute, and independent) but in ſome things moreover the writ whereby the Parliament is convee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned declares that they are not called together <hi>de omnibus, ſed de quibuſdam arduis Rebus, &amp; negotiis regentibus, &amp;c.</hi> ſome things need not Parliament Aſſemblies to determine of them, but only to conſerve them from violation, <hi>as the generall and fundamentall liberty and propriety of the ſubject, &amp;c.</hi> and as concerning that the King and Parliament are the <hi>Legiſlative power</hi> in England, I grant that they are in things <hi>diſputable,</hi> as aforeſaid, but not in things <hi>indiſputable,</hi> ſuch as is the generall and fundamentall liberty and propriety of the Subject groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Law of Nature, &amp;c. concerning their lives and eſtates, as formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And now to ſatisfie ſuch, who (by miſ-interpreting ſome places or texts of Scripture) ſuppoſe it moſt unlawfull and heynous for a Nation or People to defend by Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a naturall, or rather Nationall power (whether Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or Potency it makes no matter) their Lawes and liberties if violated; I have thought good to diſcuſſe and reſolve ſome of their chiefeſt Allegations; and firſt, that of the 13. to the Romans, <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher power for there is no power but of God, &amp;c.</hi> Concerning which Text, I ſay, that every ſoule ought to be ſubject to the higher power, ſo far forth as that power doth lawfully extend (for God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth no unlawfull thing) either by divine Law, or by Law of Nature, or by Law of Nations: Power by Divine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112149:10"/> Law is that which hath extraordinary or ſpeciall appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by God; (as I have already inſtanced in the beginning) that of Nature is grounded upon common principles of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; that of Nations upon prudent and politicall reaſons and conſiderations: Now to this laſt Power ſubjection may bee due more or leſſe; for ſome Nations have agreed and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted as it were to be ſlaves, as the Perſians, Muſcovites, Turkes, &amp;c. others have made a better bargaine for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in matters of ſubjection, as the Engliſh, Aragonez, &amp;c. Now when the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher power, &amp;c.</hi> he intends not that ſuch as were leſſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſhould make themſelves ſlaviſh by undergoing any kind of needleſſe or enforced ſubjection; but only that they ſhould be ſo far forth ſubject as God had made, or cauſed them to be ſubject: And the Apoſtle infers as much in the ſame Chapter, v. 7. <hi>Render therefore to all their dues, tribute to whom tribute; cuſtome to whom cuſtome, feare to whom feare; honour to whom honour:</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>Render more then is due if it be exacted:</hi> Moreover the Apoſtle in the words, <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject, &amp;c.</hi> induces a generall cauſe of obedience, not a ſpeciall or in ſome caſes: for ſuppoſe the Apoſtle had ſaid, <hi>Spare, or be mercifull to all men, for there is no man but he is of God, or the Image of God;</hi> this had not prohibited, but it might have been lawfull to puniſh malefactors; ſo when the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power, for there is no power but of God, &amp;c.</hi> This hinders not but that it may bee lawfull to oppoſe Tyrants, uſurpers, and ſuch like: And when the Apoſtle ſaies farther, <hi>for whoſoever reſiſteth the power reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the ordinance of God, &amp;c.</hi> it muſt ſurely be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of power one way, or other <hi>lawfull</hi> (as the 3. v. in the ſame Chapter, and the verſes following ſhew) for if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the enſlaved or oppreſſed people may free themſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112149:10"/> (if they finde convenient occaſion) from their bondage (without any ſpeciall warrant from God) as did the petty Kings and people of Sodome and Gomorah, who were enſlaved, or made Tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Gen. 14. yet their leavying War (or <hi>Rebellion)</hi> was not repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, but rather countenanced by the high Prieſt in the time of the Law of Nature, and the uſurping Tyrants of the Nations called enemies of juſt <hi>Abraham</hi> their aſſiſtant, who ſurely would not have aided or reſcued his brother, and the reſt of his brothers friends without ſome ſpeciall warrant from God, whereof we read of none) if their leavying of War (or <hi>Rebellion)</hi> to free themſelves from bondage had been unjuſt, but indeed the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated their War to be juſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Allegation greatly inſiſted upon (albeit I ſee no great reaſon for it) to prohibit Subjects to take Arms in any caſe of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany and oppreſſion againſt a Nationall Potentate, is the Text, Matth. 22. v. 21. <hi>Render therefore to Caeſar the things which are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, and to God the things which are Gods;</hi> whereby ſome would conclude, that all temporall eſtates of Subjects are <hi>Caeſars</hi> (or of ſuch like as <hi>Caeſar)</hi> and that therefore if <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould and would demand men to ſurrender all their eſtates into his hands they ought to doe it; or otherwiſe, if he ſhould by violence take it, they ought to permit him, and no way to reſiſt him; but I anſwer to ſuch, that there is in thoſe words not only a <hi>diſtinction</hi> of things ſpirituall and temporall, Gods and Caeſars; but alſo a <hi>limitation</hi> of things temporall; for it is not ſaid, <hi>Render all your mony, or ſubſtance to Caeſar,</hi> but <hi>the things which are Caeſars,</hi> ſo much as is due to him, his tribute mony, and ſuch like: It may be ſome <hi>Critick</hi> will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and ſay, that it is alſo ſaid, <hi>And to God, the things that are Gods,</hi> and that therefore according to this interpretation God may ſeem alſo to be limited; not ſo; for where the Text will admit of <hi>limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (as aforeſaid) there it ought to be admitted, but where it will not without incongruity, there it ought not to be admitted; when we have done all what we can do in reſpect of Gods ſervice, <hi>we are</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112149:11"/> 
               <hi>but unprofitable ſervants,</hi> we cannot punctually performe our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but we may give, or <hi>Render</hi> too much to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or <hi>Caeſars,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is</note> Potentates or Potencies; unleſſe they make it appeare that what we <hi>Render</hi> is for our good, as well as for theirs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some there are alſo who alleadge the 1 of Peter, 2. 13. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves to every ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake; whether it be to the King as ſupreme, &amp;c.</hi> and hence they would infer that all Acts, or Ordinances of Kings ought to be obeyed, or otherwiſe undergone and ſuffered, they muſt not be reſiſted: But ſurely Acts 4. v. 19. and alſo 5. v. 19. in things touching God, their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ought not to be obeyed, if oppoſite to the Ordinances of God; and for <hi>Ordinances of man,</hi> it ſeems that the Apoſtle meant that they ſhould ſubmit themſelves only to ſuch as were legall by the Law of Nature and Nations; as the very next verſe imports, <hi>or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him, for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of evill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well:</hi> Now the Apoſtle could not call any thing <hi>well done</hi> (for good there was none amongſt the Heatheniſh Kings, and in his daies there were no Chriſtian Kings neither in old Babilon, or new; but if there were it maketh no matter) I ſay the Apoſtle could not call any thing or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by man, or <hi>of the Ordinance of man, well done,</hi> but ſuch as ſhould be congruous to the Law of Nature and Nations; ſuch thing or things which albeit they were not <hi>de Evangelio,</hi> yet they were not <hi>contra Evangelium;</hi> ſuch as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of; that the Heathens without the Law written, did according to the Law, to the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of ſuch naturall, and nationall things doth the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> command obedience, when he ſaies, <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, &amp;c.</hi> but not to unjuſt Ordinances, for that he could not meane if contrary to the Law of God, or of Nature and Nations.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Others greatly inſiſt upon the 2. and 4. verſes of the eight Chapter of the Booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> viz. <hi>I counſell thee to keep the Kings commandement, and that in regard of the oath of God,—where</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:112149:11"/> 
               <hi>the word of a King is, there is power, and who may ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</hi> Firſt, it is to be noted that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes of a King who had (as almoſt all the Kings of the Eaſt his neighbours had) <hi>Poteſtatem vitae, &amp; necis ad placitum,</hi> and were in a manner abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; and ſuch a one was <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelfe upon the matter; for the people of Iſrael, when they deſired a King, deſired ſuch a one as all the Nations had, 1 Sam. 8. 5. and thoſe were ſuch as I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, eſpecially thoſe of their neighbour Kings; inſomuch that God was angry or diſpleaſed with the people, that they would put themſelves into ſo great a bondage, as to deſire or become ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſuch a King, or Kings of ſuch a nature; &amp; therefore God bad <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhew them the nature of <hi>ſuch a King;</hi> Now <hi>Solomon</hi> by way of <hi>counſell,</hi> or prudent policie adviſeth men to keepe the <hi>(legall)</hi> commandements of ſuch a King <hi>(illegall</hi> he could not adviſe) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they had ſworne to him (in the name of God as it ſeems) to do ſo: And if (as I have already inſtanced) a man become a ſlave to the great <hi>Turke, or ſweare ſlavery to him,</hi> he ought to perform it, for he hath ſworne it in the name of God; but if not, hee is not bound, he ought rather to make uſe of his freedome, according to that of the 1 Cor. 7. v. 21.—and as for the words, <hi>who may ſay to him what doſt thou?</hi> it is true, ſuch Kings were uncontroleable; but our Kings are not Kings of ſuch a nature, we only ſweare to be true and loyall to them <hi>de jure Regnandi, (viz.</hi> that wee in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience believe them to be our lawfull Kings, and that wee will defend their Crowne, Dignities, &amp;c. to the uttermoſt of our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) which, God forbid, any one ſhould ſo much as imagine to deprive our Kings of; but we ſweare not to our Kings that they ſhall be the abſolute diſpoſers <hi>de jure Regni,</hi> we have otherwiſe conditioned; and therefore we are not any way comprehended in or by the before recited Texts to become ſlaviſh by keeping, or obeying all <hi>Commandements</hi> of our Kings of what nature ſoever: There are ſome other Texts of Scripture of the nature of theſe laſt recited, and reducible to the ſame expoſition.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:112149:12"/>
            <p n="5">5. Yet furthermore, I will inſtance one Text, Matth. 5. v. 39. <hi>But I ſay unto yee reſiſt not evill, &amp;c.</hi> Hence ſome will that free Subjects ought to ſuffer all indignities, oppreſſions and tyrannies, rather then to <hi>reſiſt or defend themſelves by Armes:</hi> But it is to be noted, that the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that Textis, that where Gods name may by ſuffering be magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, there men ought to ſuffer all indignities, rather then to reſiſt; but where Gods name may by ſuffering be rather diſhonoured, then magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, there men ought <hi>not to ſuffer actually but intentionally:</hi> as thus, A Judge if a baſe fellow ſhould ſtrike him on the one eare or cheek, ought to have ſo much <hi>patience,</hi> as that he could turne the other; yet he ought not actually to doe it, leſt his Authority, and the Lawes of the Land alſo ſhould ſuffer contempt: And a King, if an uſurper ſhould endeavour to diſpoſe of his Scepter (or lawfull power exerciſed ought to have ſo much <hi>humility,</hi> as that he could let him have his Crowne alſo, or right of Reigning) but yet he ought not <hi>actually</hi> to doe it, leſt he injure not only his Regall Authority, but alſo his Subjects in generall, whoſe wellfare he is bound to protect: And even ſo likewiſe, a people, if a Nationall Potent, or Potencie ſhould tyrannize or oppreſſe them, ought (if it were poſſible all of them) to have ſo much <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>humility,</hi> as that they could ſuffer all indignities, yet they ought not alwaies to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them, leſt (in ſome caſes) by too much ſuffering, the Law of God, of Nature, and of their Nation (all which they are bound to conſerve) ſhould be violated: in the Chapter before recited, v. 22. it is forbidden to call a brother <hi>foole,</hi> yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> called the Galathians fooles, or foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Gal. 3. But how? out of admonition and compaſſion, not in hate or contempt, but <hi>in ordine ad Deum,</hi> to reprove, and adviſe them; and every act morall is ſpecified by the object and end; ſo that if a People (to whom <hi>jus Regni</hi> belongs) take Armes to defend their <hi>Laws and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, &amp;c.</hi> they doe it not out of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> but <hi>in ordine ad Deum,</hi> to reduce and reforme uſurping or exorbitant <hi>Potentates</hi> or <hi>Potencies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I conclude for the preſent, praying the Almighty Governour of all things, that King, Parliament and People, might in a happy union enjoy their juſt Power, Priviledge and Proprieties. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM BALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
